[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
SE-R SC radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
software for software engineering radio
this is Sam tagert I am here today with
M Scott Ford Scott is a co-founder and
CTO of Corgi bites he regularly conducts
training courses on AAL learning
platform in LinkedIn learning Scott is
the host of the podcast Legacy code
rocks and manages their slack Group
which I'm a part of that is how I met
Scott Scott is here to talk to us today
about a tool is built to manage
dependency
freshness so first of all Scott let's
talk about defining dependencies what do
you mean by the word
dependencies yeah so I think in general
it's best to think of it as code that
you didn't write that you're pulling
into your application from somewhere
else so how are you typically pulling
that code in is it through a package
manager both it's varied kind of across
history of programming so I think in the
days of your would have been like you
know copying and pasting from another
source or copying a file into your
project directly or buying a thirdparty
product that had to be installed into
your system with an installer so like
you know there are like dlls that were
installed that way and then also in some
ecosystems you know those those pieces
of code that you're consuming from
elsewhere are either part of the
operating system or can be installed
with an operating system package manager
but for most modern programming language
environments there is some kind of
dependency manifest file that allows you
to specify the packages and libraries
that you're depending on and optionally
what versions of of each of those
libraries you want to consume cool so
you mentioned versioning plays a very
important role in managing freshness so
can you kind of talk a little bit about
that yeah so freshness there are
multiple ways to Define it first let me
take a step back and and say that the
term dependency freshness was introduced
in in a paper by Joel Cox at all I
forget the name of the paper but the
idea is that how out of date the version
you're using is and there's different
ways to measure how it's out of date so
you can look at the version number and
you can kind of compare components of
the version number that you're using to
components of a later version number and
get a a distance between between the
version you're using and another version
you know whether it's the latest version
or the latest for the series that you're
targeting or or whatnot the metric that
I like the most is one that's called
liar and it's also referred to in the
paper as like a like a a Time based kind
of temporal
distance so it's looking at the release
date of the version of the package
you're on and comparing that with the
release date of the latest version and
you get a distance in years and so if
it's been six months between the version
that you're using and the release date
of the latest version then the liar for
that package will be 0 five you know
because you know half a year being six
months now I kind of see that giving
some problems because certain projects
have more churn are releasing more often
than others there's probably some
projects that are stable only get reved
like once a year or something when they
find a bug versus projects that maybe
are in development and are constantly
turning out new versions is is there a
way to account for that or this this
method just doesn't take that into
account yeah unfortunately this method
doesn't take that into account you know
there are you know some of the other
freshness measures if you key them to
like you want to stay on the major
version that you're on but you want to
make sure that you are always on the
latest minor version right you can look
at distance measures that will help you
compute that but liar just on its
surface you know is always comparing
against the latest so it is a little bit
of a weakness in in that another
weakness
is that freshness doesn't really
communicate quality of the dependency
itself so you know there are other
factors to consider as well such as is
the package that you're using is it
still being updated by you know
Community Support or a vendor or has it
been abandoned so you know you might be
on the latest version so you're you know
your dependency freshness score would be
would look really good because you're on
the latest version but that version
isn't in itself like eight years old or
something like that and that's not
necessarily a bad thing like you said
like it could be really stable it could
be just an easy to understand problem
the things that it depends on doesn't
don't change often so it doesn't it
doesn't have a need to change or it
could be that you know there's just not
any more work on it and you know it's
not receiving bug fixes it's not
receiving security updates it's not
getting operating system updates to
support you know newer environments or
newer processor architectures those are
those are also possibilities so I think
you know sometimes these things warrant
investigation and I think there are
different trends that you can you can
start to look for and you can start to
spot so like you know if you've got a
dependency that you're on the latest
version but that version is more than 5
years old then maybe it's worth
investiga or four years old or three
years old you whatever your threshold
might be maybe it warrants investigating
has the community abandoned that package
and is it time to look for an
alternative so I think there are kind of
signals that will start to show up in
the data that you can look for and then
start to use those as targets for for
further investigation so I think this
brings us to a very important question
which is why is dependency freshness
important right what possible things
have you seen go wrong when dependencies
are old and out of date yeah so to me it
shows up in three different ways there's
kind of three factors and depending on
your organization each of these factors
will have a varying degree of importance
one is Staff turnover so most teams that
I've worked on the developers on that
team get frustrated when they have to
work with libraries at consistently out
of date it becomes a a productivity
challenge as well so but that's the
second Factor so sorry keeping with that
first Factor so as people get more and
more frustrated they will eventually not
want to work on the project anymore and
then look for a job elsewhere so that is
a factor and it is a very real factor
for some teams especially when there are
lots of opportunities for software
developers to seek other form of
employment at other
organizations you know that can be a
really big challenge for teams is is
managing turnover and so I think you
know it does create a little bit of
turnover risk and probably recruiting on
that part too right so some people want
to leave and new people come in and if
they're interviewing and you say we're
using 10year old
technology that probably gets yeah yeah
and I've heard it joked that a lot a lot
of developers perform resumé driven
development where they like to pick the
tools that are going to make their their
resum may look good for the next for the
next gig and if the work that they're
doing right now isn't going to help them
further their career and make it easier
for them to get the next opportunity
then they feel like they're starting to
take on some career risk as well so I
think that is a really real problem I
think it's really hard to quantify I
think it's hard to notice when you when
you're getting into that situation it is
real now the frustration that those
individuals are experiencing is often in
the form of it being harder to work with
an older dependency because of the
information that is out there about the
projects so typically my experience has
been and I can I can definitely speak
from personal experience on
this when I'm working on an older
version of a library or working with an
older version of a library and I'm
trying to investigate how to do
something with it so there's a problem
that I'm trying to solve or I've
encountered an issue that I'm trying to
work around or I'm trying to solve a
problem in new way and I'm doing a lot
of research what I often find is that
the resources that I'm directed to are
for newer versions than the version that
I'm using because what often happens in
libraries and packages is as challenges
are encountered by members of the
community the people maintaining these
packages start to solve some of those
common problems in subsequent versions
so you can often find yourself in a
situation where the problem that you're
having has been solved by the the
community but it's been done so in a
version that's newer than the one that
you're on and if there are impediments
to to you being able to upgrade then
that becomes becomes really challenging
so my reaction to that was actually a
different reaction in that I've had the
opposite problem using Linux a lot
because for newer versions of Linux some
of the problems that you encounter
because it's newer not as many people
have run into that problem and so I
Google how do I do XYZ in Linux and all
documentations for some older version of
L where they've now updated all the
tools and it works differently so that's
just an interesting data point yeah and
then the the third component for why
freshness is important is security and
then for a lot of organizations this is
the one that's most important and that's
that security vulnerabilities don't get
fixed in the exact version you're using
right like you're you're targeting a
specific version of a third party
project and so by incorporating that
into your into your code base
if there's a vulnerability in that third
party dependency there's now a
vulnerability or potential for
vulnerability in your code base now you
might not be exercising the library in a
way that would expose your project to
the vulnerability but the risk is
certainly higher than it would be
otherwise if there wasn't a
vulnerability in the third party
dependency so you will need to be able
to upgrade to a version of the library
that doesn't have that vulnerability
so looking at freshness and starting to
consider you know a measure of freshness
being how many known vulnerabilities are
there in a package right so like the
idea being that if your library is
supported by a community that's that's
very active and stays on top of security
vulnerabilities and patches them
relatively quickly then the latest
version should not have any known
vulnerabilities right there should or
there should be at least a version
of that project with no known
vulnerabilities and you can Target that
version and so the the number of
vulnerabilities and the levels and
severity of those
vulnerabilities can start to be used to
kind of form an additional freshness met
metric kind of separate from the version
number
itself yes that's interesting so you're
not only relying
on the the new version but you're also
relying on the maintainers so that in a
way when there's a bug the maintainers
actually have to go and issue a new
update right so if the bug is found and
nobody fixes it that also doesn't vode
well yeah and so if there's not
community support for that you've
adopted this this dependency into your
into your project and so when you become
aware of the fact that there's a
vulnerability you now have a
responsibility to make sure that that
gets fixed and you know it could be
really understanding the vulnerability
and making sure they're on any code
paths in your application that that
bring it to life so to speak or it could
be finding a way for you to for you to
fix it or patch that Library Yourself by
forking it and creating your own version
that speaks to the value of having open
source dependencies yes yeah because
that becomes possible Right whereas with
a a Clos Source third party dependency
it's much less possible it's not
impossible it's much less possible yeah
to get into fix things yourself yeah in
that case the best you can do is try to
prevent that code path from being
executed or do some kind of
mitigation so how do developers
currently manage this freshness and
keeping stuff up to date without talking
about your product yet freshly like if
people aren't using that how do they
handle this problem yeah so there are a
variety of approaches and there is
starting to be better and better tooling
kind of introduced to help teams stay on
top of the challenge and stay on top of
the problem most package managers have a
command that you can run that is like
usually outdated or something along
those lines so there's like npm space
outdated there's uh bundle outdated I
think there is at least or if not
there's a plugin for it so there are
different package management communities
there's like new get outdated as well
there are different package management
communities where you can kind of get a
list of the versions that you're
depending on and what are the latest
versions that are available and they
usually present it in a variety of ways
so it'll show you the the way that the
version has been specified in your
application and you can specify versions
usually in a multiple number of ways you
can specify an exact version number or
you can specify an expression that will
resolve to an exact version number and
most of these tools that let you know
whether or not there's a newer package
they'll let you know first if there's a
newer version that
satisfies that expression that you've
defined for the version number and it
will also show you if there's a a
version that's even newer than that to
kind of help you kind of assess which
might be easier to upgrade to so I have
a question for you you work with a lot
of Legacy code bases do you generally
prefer to specify exact version numbers
or minimum version number and and what
are the tradeoffs there yeah so I like
there to be some mechanism that
specifies the exact version number like
usually that's in the form of a lock
file so in the yarn and npm ecosystems
it's either you know packages. loock or
y. loock in the Ruby ecosystem it's gy
file. loock not sure what it is in the
net ecosystem but I know there is one
there is a lock file that does pin down
the exact version number
and those are like that is I think I
think it's important for applications at
least to be to specif the exact version
number that you expect to install
especially like when comparing a local
development environment with a
production environment you want to be
able to have those two environments
relatively in sync with the version
numbers that are getting installed
otherwise you can run into potential
problems with production have an older
version of a of a package and the bug
you're trying to fix has actually been
fixed in a in a dependency but you're
not able to observe that bug because
you've got a newer version of that
dependency locally
so it is important to have some kind of
mechanism for keeping those in sync and
if the package manager that you're using
doesn't provide that mechanism then I
think you do have to specify exact
version numbers yeah yeah that's kind of
like the uh works on my machine problem
exactly yeah so when you do have ranges
available to you so if you're able to
kind of kind of partner ranges with
exact versions then I think it makes
sense to look at the waiver version
numbers are being specified for the
dependency that you're using and specify
the version range in a in such a way
that you're able to absorb any new
versions that don't have any breaking
changes that's kind of a promise that
the package main Changers are making to
you is that certain version number
increments won't have breaking changes
included there's the Sim ver or semantic
versioning convention that specifies
which parts of a version number are
allowed to change based on what changes
of been introduced as part of that
version so if there's a breaking change
the first digit and the version number
is supposed to increment as an example
so if the project that you're consuming
complies with sver then you can say that
like the major version that you're on
you want to keep that the same but then
all newer versions are acceptable and
then you might specify like a minimum
version within that category so it could
be that you started a feature that your
application needs was introduced in say
3.5 and so anything less than 40 is okay
but it needs to be greater than
okay so how common do you think it is
for companies and projects to have out
ofd dependencies is it widespread crazy
common crazy common yeah there's a
report the ossr report from
2023 so nearly half of Commercial Code
bases contain a known high-risk
vulnerability that has been
patched and it's 48% of those code bases
so that's a data point where we can
point to and say like these are known
vulnerabilities that are present and
there's a fix for these vulnerabilities
right so that means those packages have
to be out of date right like doesn't
happen any way I don't know of like
specific data for like how many how many
companies have what percentage of their
code base is out of date or what not but
I think like that number tells us a lot
in and of itself yeah and if people want
to know about the consequence of that
they could probably just go Google
Equifax because that is the the shining
example that everybody knows
about that example is what really got me
really interested in this area and kind
of dependency freshness in general and
it was specifically when I read an
article that was published by ARS
Technica where they reported that it was
Apache struts so that was vulnerability
in the Apache struts Library so the
Apache struts web framework
that was being used by Equifax the
vulnerability was was published and at
the same time that the vulnerability was
published The Fix was released and it
was two months after that publication
that Equifax was hacked and the the
vulnerability that they that was
exploited was one that was that was
fixed prior to that two-month window so
the development team had had two months
to patch it now I've worked on Plenty of
development teams where
upgrading a major dependency such as
like uh Apache struts like something
that's like that's absolutely for a web
project that's absolutely foundational
and presents a high level of risk for
upgrading but to me their inability to
do that within two months to me
communicates a pattern of practice
within the development team where it had
become hard to do upgrades and it wasn't
routine and so I think teams need to get
to the point where doing upgrades of
these sort becomes routine and so you
were you were asking about tools earlier
dependabot is another great tool for
this there are other other tools that
that have similar capabilities but it
will it will notice that there's a newer
version of a package that you're
depending on and it will open up a p
request for you that patches that
package and you can look and see if your
test Suite passes and so if you've got a
strong enough safety net to help you
notice when upgrading a package is going
to break something then you can start to
to build some trust that upgrading isn't
going to break
anything that needs to be said with a
giant caveat however because there have
been some sophisticated vulnerabilities
that have been inserted exploiting that
practice and these are known as supply
chain attacks where a bad actor has
gotten access to the source code
repository of a popular library and
they've inserted militia code and
released a new version so you know
pretty much the only change in that
version is the inclusion of this
malicious code so there is a previous
episode of software engineering radio
that covers that and I do not have a
number off the top of my head but we can
throw it in the show notes so you start
to answer my next question my next
question is going to be why do
organizations struggle with out ofate
dependencies I think you hit on one
reason is that it's hard to upgrade and
people are afraid of breaking their code
when they upgrade and they don't have
the test infrastructure around that but
what other reasons is it lack like from
an organizational standpoint is it lack
of info or visibility is it incentives
is it sometimes they just don't care or
don't know I think it's I think it's
sometimes all of those things or all of
them at once or any number of them I
think that awareness is is a big part of
the problem when projects get created
from scratch they're almost always using
the latest versions of things and then
they just continue to work right like
those those versions that you're
depending on they're just continuing to
work and very much within the vein of
it's not broken don't fix it there's not
really a big need or a big motivator to
keep things up to date and so it can be
easy to kind of not maintain that
awareness as a result I also think that
on teams where there is awareness that
there are problems and that those
problems are caused by things being out
of date there's often a situation where
leadership doesn't see the value in
investing and making a change that
doesn't provide any any new
functionality so upgrading a third-
party dependency if done
correctly it's not a user visible change
or if the if there is a user visible
change it's because things are faster
hopefully hopefully not things are
slower but like usually there's a
performance impact or maybe there's a
bug that gets fixed but you're not going
to get a new feature as a result like
you're not going to upgrade a third
party it's it's going to be pretty rare
that you upgrade a third- partyy
dependency and now you have new
capabilities that you're able to offer
your customers just by upgrading the
dependency that newer version might
allow you to then build upon the
features in that new version to provide
value to your customers but there are a
lot of Business Leaders that you don't
see the value in in that investment and
then the issue that I mentioned before
in that a lot of teams kind of view it
as a as a risk in that a lot of these
dependencies are many of them are
foundational
or they're only used in a very small
part of the code and both have problems
so the ones that are foundational you
have the risk that it'll break
everything and that's often what people
are afraid of but there's also the risk
that it's going to break something in a
very like nuanced minor way because just
because the the team that's put out the
new version just because they they're
shipping bug fixes they're shipping
performance enhancements they're
shipping security vulnerability
remediations it's still possible that
they've introduced to new bugs there's
no way for us to solve the halting
problem so introducing change into your
into your system is introducing risk and
and so you know that ends up becoming a
risk that you need to manage and there
are a lot of teams that are pretty risk
averse when it comes to things breaking
and I think that's largely because they
don't have very thorough tests
around whether or not their dependencies
are doing what they expect them to do so
that brings me to a question when it
comes to dependencies and testing do you
typically recommend that you write tests
around the libraries that you depend on
or do you just test those as part of
your tests for the rest of your code
like some some path is calling that
dependency and therefore it gets tested
yeah so for the the approach that's best
taken kind of depends on the kind of a
dependency that you're working with I
think for a foundational dependency such
as like a web
framework that is best tested just as
part of like having end to-end
acceptance tests so tests that exercise
the full stack because that's going to
be exercising that dependency and the
work that that that dependency is
providing you will get exercised as as
part of that if it's a dependency that's
providing you like one specific
capability like maybe it takes maybe it
takes a Word document and generates a
PDF or something of that sort right like
it has a very small nuan task I think in
those cases it makes sense to have like
a small integration test that exercises
that dependency and makes sure that it
it continues to work the way you expect
it to you don't need to exhaust possibly
test it like the team that's releasing
it is going to be testing it but test
what you need out of it right like test
that it's providing you what what you
need out of it and again those don't
need to be extensive but really trying
to think about like okay if there was a
breaking change that was introduced I
would want this test to fail if you're
using a dynamic language where the
compiler isn't able to kind of isn't
able to notify you about breaking
changes like that then you would want
your test to fail if it breaking changes
like that was introduced or looking at
the output of what gets generated and
making sure that it's equivalent to what
you expect it to be and if it's not then
that means a bug was introduced as part
of that dependency and you probably only
need like maybe one or two of those for
those kind of minor dependencies but for
the more foundational dependencies it's
next to impossible to really exercise
every everything you're utilizing from
it because often the design of those
foundational dependencies really
influence the design of your application
and testing your application and
isolation of those dependencies really
requires a completely different
architecture for your application than
is commonly commonly used so if you've
adopted such an architecture like a
hexon architecture then you can leverage
some of the test points that are
available within that but if you haven't
if you've just kind of like you just
quickly built on top of it then there's
not a lot of utility in testing those
dependencies
independently okay so let's move on and
talk about just freshly itself can you
give me a brief summary like what is
freshly how does it relate to all the
stuff we've been talking about yeah so
and it's it's gone through a few a few
iterations and it's it's definitely
something that continuing to work on and
continuing to reimagine and evolve into
something better based on feedback from
people I'm sharing it with but it really
started out as a experiment
for graphing how dependency fresh
metrics changed over time so taking the
data out of a dependency manifest file
Computing dependency freshness metrics
for the dependencies that are specified
in there but not leaving it at that
there are a lot of tools that compute
liar there's there's probably if you go
to li.com there's there's a good list of
of tools and there's probably one for
the language that you're using it will
read your dependency manifest file and
it'll spit out the liby your value for
all of your packages what I was really
interested in is how those values change
over time and what what they might be
communicating about the team's behavior
and about how things are trending for
them what they might communicate about
the community of dependencies that are
being relied on so what freshley does is
it looks at the history within within
get and for as much history as it as it
can get access to it computes the the
libar metric across that time by default
it does this in one month month
intervals and it computes the metric as
it would have been at that point in time
so if it's looking at like you know
January 1st three years ago then what
would the dependency freshness you know
liar metric look like at that at that
point in time and so then then able to
graph that for teams and then show how
these values have trended over
time I also wanted freshly to be
supportive of ecosystems and and project
structures where there were multiple
dependency manifest files that are
present and I wanted it to be a a tool
that supported multiple language
communities so which languages do you
support yeah so in the like the first
initial version we had which you can you
can play with by going to
freshly.com
poser Ruby via bundler uh python via
requirements. text
file.net via looking at CS project files
and I think that was it and then maybe
Pearl using a like a cpan file the
initial approach that was taken there
was to write code in the host language
the the language that freshly was being
built with which we ended up we pick C
but write code dep parse the dependency
manifest file formats in these other
ecosystems and that worked pretty well
for you know those initial targets you
know Ruby PHP python that worked pretty
well and then we were writing inside the
do head ecosystem so tooling was readly
available for uh you know apis were
available for us to to do this work in
inet one thing we did start to notice is
that we felt like we were duplicating
effort we knew that there were libraries
in these host ecosystems that already
knew how to parse these files and
already knew how to do the the
dependency resolution for an expression
and things like that and so but we were
having to like reimplement all that
logic and there was risk that we would
get it wrong and we did have a lot of
initial initial bugs at first where we
we did get some of those things
wrong so that had us kind of wishing
that we could you know kind of Leverage
code that already existed in those
ecosystems and then when we went to go
at support for the JavaScript ecosystem
specifically yarn yarn's lock file
format
is non-trivial to parse and then also so
when we started looking at the Java
ecosystem specifically with Maven the
pom.xml file and the various ways that
versions can be specified and the
various ways that pom.xml files can
refer to other pom.xml
files that just seemed like way too big
for us to for us to reimplement and so
we ended up pivoting to an approach
where we have a core CLI
application that knows how to do things
like compute liar based on a common file
format at but then we have language
agent programs that are written in the
host ecosystem and are able to leverage
apis in that host ecosystem and then the
CLI communicates with those so we've got
under that approach the newer version of
the CLI is done for the most part
there's obviously still things that we'd
like to add and then we've got a
language agent built for Java and we've
got a language agent built for forn net
and we have ones in progress for go and
python so the language agent Cent are
like a plug-in type system it is very
much like a plug-in like system it's a
plugin that isn't executable so in that
executable when you start it runs a a
grpc service that the CLI is is
communicating with you know that the
central CLI is communicating with so
then the CLI is responsible for like
walking through the the history of of
the G repository and figuring out like
what points in time need to be analyzed
and what G Shaws need to be looked at
it's responsible for doing that and and
then it asks the it asks the language
agents to detect any dependency
manifests in a particular file tree and
then it asks it to create a software
build of materials we're using the
Cyclone DX as bomb format for
that engineering workflows can be a mess
from prioritizing Sprint tasks to
explaining technical diagrams you're
spending more time explaining work and
less time doing it mirro brings all your
work together seamlessly in one online
visual workspace create diagrams inl or
mermaid run sprints and create jira or
Azure tasks in Miro instantly go from
idea to action without switching to
different tools get your first three
boards free when you sign up today at
mirro.com
podcast that's M
o.com
podcast
let's continue just talking
about the plugins and the different
ecosystems yeah yeah and then and then
the central CLI is also responsible for
communicating with the API that the data
gets transmitted to so you can then view
the graphs on the website that's how
that architecture is set up so the the
language agent plugins are really only
responsible for you looking at detecting
dependency manifest files in a directory
tree and then converting those into an
sbom format so that the CLI can then can
then work with it so what the CLI does
is it it uses the es bomb file to
compute the libar metric so while we're
talking about es bombs I want to talk
about later but let's just talk about
now you had talked about security
earlier and I think this kind of ties
into that so what is an sbom yeah so
it's a software build of materials and
it is a a structured document that
specifies all of the thirdparty
dependencies that an application is
using it can specify things other than
that you can craft an s bomb to also
communicate the third-party like web
enabled services that you're
communicating with and then esoms can
also you can communicate other other
forms of metadata as well such as like
the license that's being used so they're
a pretty good file format for different
kinds of analyses especially the Cyclone
DX file format because the Cyclone DX
file format has the ability to also
include information about
vulnerabilities that are known for the
packages so from a single file format
you can do analysis for what licenses
are being used across across your
project so you can kind of get a you can
do some due diligence around do you have
exposure for license violations like are
you consuming code that has a copy left
license that you may or may or may not
be complying with or maybe your
organization has a policy that like a
particular license just isn't allowed
that file format and the tools that can
generate for you can help you do that
analysis it also includes in it a a tree
of the dependencies that you're using
and the tools that generate these can be
usually configured as to whether or not
they include
dependencies that are used for
development versus development
production so you know depending on what
you're interested in you can adjust them
that way and so you can kind of see the
version numbers that you're using also
there's usually a hash of those versions
so you get some kind of like
cryptographic check of what that code
should look like so then you can kind of
do tests against different deployment
environments to see if your dependencies
have been modified so that's another
thing that it can be that it can be used
for is to kind of make sure that the
correctness of those files is still good
that those dependencies haven't been
modified by bad
actor okay so the sbom then lists all
the dependencies in the tree it lists
the version it has a hash it has
potentially
vulnerabilities yeah potentially
vulnerabilities it has licensed
information it'll likely have author
information links to documentation
there's a lot of metadata that can be
embedded in there and it really kind of
depends on the tool vendor that you're
using and how much data they provide and
also how much data they're able to to
get from the projects that you know
publish these packages okay and the
reason s bombs are in the news is
because there's talk at least of the
government requiring them for certain
things right or maybe they already are
required for yes so there was an
executive order signed a couple years
ago by the by the Biden Administration
that mandates that they that they're
created in in different scenarios I
don't know all of those scenarios nor do
I know I'm not super aware of like what
the requirements for for what an sbom
needs to needs to have in it in order to
comply with that but it is a file format
that that teams are starting to starting
to be aware of and one thing that I
think is really nice about it is that
prior to these sbom based tools being
introduced you know you had lots of
different language ecosystems with
fragmented ways of defining these
dependency trees in the sbom file
formats and there's two competing two
pretty prominent competing standards the
spdx and the DX or is spdx the one that
I'm not used to working
with Cyclone DX is is the one that I'm
I'm more familiar with that's the one
that we're using under the covers and
freshly and so now you don't have like
this huge fragmentation across language
boundaries that you had before okay so
if I needed to generate an s bomb for my
project I could potentially use freshly
to do that yes and that's something that
we're going to make more visible right
now the es bombs they're getting created
in a folder and a DOT freshly directory
and again because we're going back in
time we're Computing the esom as it
might have looked we're not 100% exactly
sure that it's that it's correct but as
correct as we can make it for what the
esom would have been at that point in
the past okay so what does that look
like like how do I use freshly is is it
a service that I connect up to my GitHub
account is it a program that runs
locally on my computer how does that
work our initial envisioning of it was
that it would be kind of a software as a
service thing that you would you would
connect your GitHub account to and then
do the analysis we got some feedback
from some different organizations that
were nervous about a third party service
having access to their to their source
code and we didn't want to be a target
for for getting hacked so as a way to
kind of minimize both the risk to the
codebase owners and kind of a risk
minimize the risk to ourselves we kind
of pivoted away from that approach and
so now the CLI is what does the
collecting of of the the data it's what
does the analysis and then the the
metrics that it's computed and the S
bombs are getting sent up to the freshly
API and then you'll be able to log into
the freshly website and then see the
analytics and graphs and recommendations
based on that okay so what type of
reports and graphs can I see in freshly
and then the following question is what
kind of insights can I can I get from
that because you mentioned earlier that
instead of looking at one point in time
you look over time so what does what
does that time frame tell you maybe you
can give some examples of like things
that you've noticed and then what the
solution was or what problem it pointed
out yeah I can I can certainly give some
examples so the graphs that we're
currently producing are based on on liar
and we're looking at a Project's total
Li year so we take the liar value for
each package and we add them all
together to get a composite you know
aggregate value for your whole project
or you know for the whole dependency
manifest file and graph how that's
changed over time now there are multiple
reasons that that number could go up
like it's highly sensitive to the number
of dependencies right so the more
dependencies you have the chances that
that number is higher is going to go up
so it's it's going to scale it's going
to likely scale relative to how many
dependencies you have so question though
can I look at that then as a way of like
measuring my exposure in a way because
if I have one really old dependency I
have a lot of exposures but if I have a
whole bunch of different dependencies
even if they're all relatively up to dat
that's also more exposure am I thinking
about that right yeah I think like so
I've been I've been thinking about that
like total liar as a standin for risk I
wish I knew how to convert that risk
into into Dollars like how much money is
on the line like how much Financial Risk
there is but I do think it is a measure
of some kind of risk I'm not sure what
yet but as that as that number goes up
your risk has also gone up and there's
multiple ways that that it can go up
like like you said said like it can go
up a little bit across a lot of packages
or it can go up a lot in one package
right but the level of risk that you're
that you're carrying in your project has
increased so we look at the we look at
the the total and then for applications
the the metric on the liar website they
say on their website that they try to
keep application totals to under 10
years so you know for a particular
application you know under 10 years in
their opinion is pretty good and so you
can imagine like if you've got like 100
dependencies right you know you can hit
that 10year figure by having like an
average of 0.1 yeah that was going to be
another question I had was like what
what's a good number if I'm looking at
the number like so so that that's a
question right are you more interested
in the number itself or the trend over
time I'm more interested in the trend I
think I think that the trends and and
what they can tell us is more
interesting than the numbers and so the
other graphs that I that we look at we
look at average and average pretty much
has the exact same shape like if you
were to squint you wouldn't really be
able to tell the difference between the
total graph and the average graph the
scale is different so you can kind of
you you get a sense of of what the the
scale might be and then we also graph
the max the maximum value and I think
that that's pretty interesting and
that's one that I think having some hard
thresholds on would be a good idea for
teams and that's something that we plan
on adding support for is being able to
integrate freshly into a cicd pipeline
and failing to build if the maximum
value has crossed a particular threshold
so like has the maximum value crossed a
year so is there is there at least one
Library that's more than a year old in
your code base and that could be like
just a hard threshold that your team
sets yeah and I imagine if you had one
that was stable that you didn't care
about you could potentially keep that
out of the out of the running or say if
there's one just this one that we care
about you can ignore it or something
yeah you could create an allow list or
like libraries that you that you ignore
things things of that sort but like
having some kind of way to like you know
plug into the cicd pipeline and say that
like you know these are the thresholds
that we care about like whether it's a a
thres threshold on the total a threshold
on the average or a threshold on the
maximum and then the final graph that we
put together it shows all of the
packages over time so every single
package your project has ever depended
on and what the liar values have have
been over time for those and that's the
graph that I think has shown some
interesting insights and I'll talk about
those and I'll talk about some insights
that can be gained from from some of the
others I've given talks at a couple
different python conferences and have
shown graphs from different open source
applications in the python ecosystem
what's interesting for a lot of them is
the trajectory that liar goes up before
python version 2.7 was declared dead is
a it's a very different trajectory then
after python 27 was declared dead and so
you can almost like draw a line on the
graph and it kind of shows up visually
like there's a huge spike in the in the
graph when python 27 when support
officially ended and what I suspect
happened is you had an ecosystem effect
where across the entire ecosystem of
packages package maintainers went in and
dropped support for python 27 and then
and published a new version so they were
likely able to jettison lots of code
that they've been holding on to that
they were frustrated with or might have
been a source of a bunch of bugs and so
they were able to release a new version
that that dropped support for python on
27 and then interestingly enough past
that point the liar values tend to go up
faster than they were before that so I
think that means that the velocity
across the open source projects
increased after dropping support for
python 27 it's almost like across the
ecosystem teams you know started putting
out more frequent versions of their of
their packages because they were able to
drop support for python 27 and so it's
neat to kind of see that signal show up
across multiple different applications
so I I'm thinking about that was that
cause or effect was it that they dropped
2.7 now they could go faster or was it
that they dropped 2.7 but when they
dropped that support they introduced
some new bugs that then they immediately
had to fix yeah yeah yeah I think both
are plausible so yeah cause versus
effect there can be difficult to tease
out but I think I think that kind of
gets to a point that I try to keep in
mind with a lot of these graphs and with
a lot of metrics in general is the value
isn't good or bad on its own right like
it can be high or low but low and high
might necessarily have you know good or
bad connotations right it's it's high
values warrant more investigation than
low values is the way that I look at it
right and so you want to make sure that
you can understand the reason for
whatever value you have like if if the
value is low and it's been low for for a
while make sure you understand make sure
you understand why it's low you know
it's low because the team's doing a good
job keeping update with the packages or
it's low because all the packages of the
teams depending on aren't being updated
anymore so you know kind of really
looking at that and and figuring out
making sure that you kind of understand
why the graph you have has the shape
that it has another thing that shows up
on a lot of the average graphs the total
and the average graph is when teams put
in investment to to do like a major
framework upgrade so in a lot of Ruby on
Rails applications that I've analyzed
with freshley the total lier kind of
does this stair step up and to the right
and then there will be like this drop
where where like there'll be like a 50%
reduction in the score the next major
when the team is upgraded to the next
major version of rails and then it kind
of like continues to go up at the same
the same rate that it was going up
before and then there'll be another
investment and it'll drop by like 50%
again but something that I've noticed on
these graphs is that it never gets
brought back down to really low like
it's it's you know the trend is still up
and to the right the trend is still ever
increasing even though the team has been
putting in an effort to bring it down at
different points in time and effort
shows up and can be observed on the
graphs and on projects that we analyzed
for clients of ours we're able to then
correlate with like based on our time
sheets from that point in time like what
we were working on I'm like oh yeah that
that is when we were working on a rails
upgrade like that that big drop in the
graph is when we did this work and so
you know it's a way that can that it can
show up and kind of be a a measure of
you know how much return did you get on
the investment that you put in yeah I
wonder if the constant increasing is
just a form of
entropy right like time just keeps
marching on and as time goes on you're
adding more features so you're
potentially adding more dependencies and
it's just kind of inevitable that it
eventually just keeps going up yeah and
I think like you know if you think of
freshness as a technical debt measure
right or a technical debt metric then I
think it's kind of unique amongst those
technical debt metrics because with most
of them they only change when the source
code changes so if you think about like
different different ways to compute
complexity whether it's architecture
complexity or you know individual code
you know method complexity those values
will only change of the source code
changes but with freshness freshness
will continue to change even if the
source code doesn't change so the whole
attitude of like let's not touch it it's
not broken it does start to show up
there is extra risk that you're carrying
even though you're not making changes to
the to the system well I think that
carries with my understanding of
technical debt because if you wrote
something 10 years ago and it was
written perfect at that time and you
look at it today most people would
consider that technical debt even though
the code hasn't changed since they wrote
it then so so that kind of tracks I
think yeah and some things that we wna
we want to get better at and we want to
find some some good solutions for are
being able to to track the the versions
of the major tooling that's being used
also like the version of the compiler
that's being used to build a project or
the version of the runtime uh that's
being used there's not always clear
manifests for that information but where
we can get it we're going to start
surfacing that as well it's not like a
traditional dependency that you might
think of in terms of like a package that
you're relying on but most compilers or
or interpreters do ship with a standard
Library you can think of that you know
that standard Library being the
dependency uh and sometimes there are
vulnerabilities that do get exposed in
those standard libraries well that's
interesting because I do a lot of work
in Labby and we talk to a lot of
hardware and so sometimes the hardware
drivers right there's a there's that lab
view package that talks to the hardware
driver but then the hardware driver has
its own version and then sometimes even
the hardware itself has its own firmware
versions which would probably be
interesting and good to track as well
yeah and I think like you know that use
case of like communicating with an
external device or kind of you know
communicating with anything anything
external anything your team doesn't
control I think a practice that I
learned from working in Aerospace is to
build out some tests to kind of qualify
those dependencies so some test to kind
of qualify like yes I can actually talk
to the hardware and yes I'm confident
that I can talk to the hardware even if
even if it's the kind of test that
requires a little bit of manual
intervention such as like you know it's
a test that runs and then asks you to
like look at a display on the device and
then type in a
value and and incorporate that value in
the end the test suite and so you know
it could be that like the driver was
commanded to display four on a display
or to do something that would have had
the number four show up you know
somewhere on the device and then you
know you then enter that value to kind
of close the loop for the test yeah
that's definitely uh something I do a
lot of although I have to say a lot of
that tends to be manual but sometimes I
get some automated tests around those
yeah it's definitely worth uh doing
those types of things so you do a lot of
Consulting is freshly something that you
use with all your clients and that you
recommend that all your clients use is
there a time when you wouldn't recommend
it or when it doesn't add a lot of value
not that we've noticed so far we are big
limiter on using it with all of our
clients at this point is how many
languages that we've built support for
with the new architecture so like we
don't yet have support for JavaScript
that's like high on the list to add to
add in the future and then you know we
want to add support for for PHP and then
once we have those two then we'll kind
of have all of our our current clients
covered you know we'll have net and Java
and PHP and JavaScript and Ruby you know
Ruby's the other one we need to add
support for but having all that built
out will then allow us to you know
support our current customers more but
this is kind of largely borne out of a
repeated problem that we've seen over
and over across clients and and it's
something that we plan on doing more and
more often at corg byes is taking taking
repeated patterns that we've seen and
trying to productize uh solutions to
those problems and freshly is just
really our first attempt at doing so so
I I have a question then you mentioned
that one of the limiting factors of
support for different languages I I'm a
lab view programmer is there a way is
the specification open enough that I
could go write my own plugin to talk to
lab view or is that something you guys
would have to do on your end yeah so the
CLI is an open source project and the
language agents that we've written are
open source the only kind of closed
Source component is the website where
you can kind of where you can view the
view the data that's been collected in
the graphs and kind of get that get that
analysis and and and learning from that
but yeah absolutely like you could try
and create a language agent for lab view
if you want to be really interested to
talk to you about that if you're
interested in giving it a try the
documentation around that is is pretty
poor at this point like uh as it is with
many open source projects but that is
something we do have on our road map to
to definitely improve improve both the
tooling around making it easier for
people to create language agents and
then tools for kind of qualifying
whether or not the language agent
provides the capabilities that that's
needed by the
CLI very nice so one last question that
is assuming one of our listeners is
using one of the language is already
supported how do they get started a
couple different ways if you go to
Freshly doapp there are instructions for
how to download the docker container
that you can use to to run an analysis
on on your project the version that we
have in that Docker container is a
little outdated so if you happen to run
into a bug then following the
instructions for how to build a project
from Source at our our GitHub project
for the freshly CLI would be the the
next thing to tackle and those languages
that we have language agents built for
are Java using maven we don't have
Gradle support yet and then net we've
got that support for net for both CS Pro
files that have package references in
them and then also the packages. Json
format that was used for a little while
by nuget so all those uh plugins your
Callum all those language specific
things are included in the docker
container yeah the the docker container
that you'll get if you if you do the
download that right now that only has
the Java language agent and it we're
working on cleaning up the next version
it'll be 0.
6.0 and that'll have that Docker
container will have both the Java
language agent and the net language
agent installed inside of it and that's
one of the that's one of the reasons why
we're kind of taking the approach of
using Docker for the delivery is that
the following the steps to set up a an
environment correctly for all the
different language agents can can become
a non-trivial task okay but if I wanted
to I could go to your GitHub and clone
it and then build the docker container
from there and include my own lab view
yep okay absolutely very cool well thank
you Scott that was a great and
enlightening conversation thanks I
appreciate it it's been fun for software
engineering radio this has Ben Sam
tagert thanks for listening to SC radio
an educational program brought to you by
It software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
[Music]
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for